<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Dowdall's just and sober vindication, in opposition to several injustices practised against him, by some of his fellow prisoners in the gate-house prison of Westminster, although reputed priests, Jesuits, and sufferers for Christs sake</title>
            <author>Dowdall, Gerard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225596</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897941</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897941</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81686)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2554:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Dowdall's just and sober vindication, in opposition to several injustices practised against him, by some of his fellow prisoners in the gate-house prison of Westminster, although reputed priests, Jesuits, and sufferers for Christs sake</title>
                  <author>Dowdall, Gerard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 106 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed [by W. Downing] for Gerard Dowdall, in Westminster Gate-House,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Colophon reads: London printed, and are to be sold by W. Downing in Bartholomew Close printer, 1681</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library,</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prisons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prisoners --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Westminster (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132878:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132878:1"/>
            <p>Mr. Dowdall's Juſt and Sober VINDICATION, In oppoſition to ſeveral INJUSTICES Practiſed againſt him, by ſome of his Fellow Priſoners IN THE Gate-Houſe Priſon OF <hi>WESTMINSTER,</hi> Although Reputed Prieſts, Jeſuits, and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers for Chriſts ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Gerard Dowdall,</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Gate-Houſe, 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:132878:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132878:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To the moſt Vertuous, moſt Pious, and moſt charitable Ladies, the Relievers of poor Priſoners, during the late Troubleſome times, for Religion.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOthing appears more Splendent in this World, then the Heroick Actions of Men, by which they Conquor Nations, Deſtroy their Enemies, and conſequently, free themſelves from Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Thraldome, becoming thereby, not onely an everlaſting Glory to Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but alſo to the Countries and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from whence they deſcend.</p>
            <p>All thoſe, moſt Vertuous, moſt Pious, and moſt Charitable Ladies, you have far ſurpaſs'd by your unparallel'd Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Piety, and Liberality. <hi>Alexander,</hi> the Great Conqueror of the World, has
<pb facs="tcp:132878:3"/> own'd the ſame, ſaying, <hi>That who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomes himſelf, is more Praiſe Worthy, then he who takes by force of Armes the ſtrongeſt Townes or Cities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is known to thoſe that have Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled moſt parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> that none has practiſed all the degrees of Vertue more than you theſe three Years laſt paſt; and this is to <hi>overcome ones ſelf.</hi> You boar your Croſſes chearfully; you thanked God as well in your Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as in your Proſperities; you ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured your diſtreſſed Neighbours; you Comforted the Comfortleſs; you Viſited the Sick; and you did not abhor the noiſome Smells of Goals, but afforded your Almes as ſhowers of Gold to poor Priſoners; and the Dead you Buried with Joy: Theſe are the Works of Mercy, recommended by our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, the which acquir'd unto you more Honour and Glory, then ever Conquerors deſerv'd; for what doth it avail one, to gain the whole World,
<pb facs="tcp:132878:3"/> with the loſs of his Soul? By theſe good Acts, your Memories ever remain, both in this, and in the World to come. By theſe you are a Mirrour to future Ages, and which is more, you have by theſe prepared to your ſelves an everlaſting habitation with God and his Angels in Heaven: For as Water quenches Fire, ſo your Almes and good Deeds have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated the Root of your Sins. Now you will find verified the words of Chriſt, <hi>That what you have done for one of theſe little ones in Priſon, you have done it for Him.</hi> All this while 'tis to be believ'd, that all theſe forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned great and ample works of Piety, has been grounded on true Charity, which is underſtood to be done for Gods ſake alone; For what is practiſed on other reſpects, as for kindred, friendſhip, or for any other worldly Intereſt ſake, or out of a natural pity, carries its whole reward of good Name or Fame along with it. For my part, I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, your Intentions in beſtowing
<pb facs="tcp:132878:4"/> your Charities, are ſincere and real, for the Love of God only; as a certain Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow I knew, who had but an hundred pounds <hi>per annum</hi> Joynture, gave forty thereof to Relieve poor Priſoners. Pray give me leave to tell you, that your will and pleaſure in the diſtribution of your Charities, is much abuſed; You have one end therein, and ſome of your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants or Truſtees another; You intend doubtleſs, that your Charities be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Honour and Glory of God, according to the Priſoners neceſſities and Qualities; But on the contrary, your Truſtees, reſolves to give the ſame to thoſe they love and fancy moſt, but whether that be well or ill grounded, God and their own Conſcience muſt be Judge. There are ſome detained Priſoners for want of Monys to procure their <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and to pay their Chamber Rent: but you had rather contribute ſo much a week for the Releaſe of ſuch Priſoners, then allow them a maintenance in Priſon; but your Truſtees wholly reject ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſalls,
<pb facs="tcp:132878:4"/> by which they hinder the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners Liberty, and put you to unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary charges for their Maintenance: One or two of them gave your Moneys freely to diſcharge the expences requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the Releaſe of a Stranger they had a kindneſs for; and another at the ſame time and place, and on the ſame account, although well known to moſt Catholicks in Town, could not prevail to have a penny from them. Happy is he in theſe dayes, that is young and handſome, which ſome of your Truſtees regard more than the fulfilling of your pleaſures; yet to juſtifie themſelves in their Extravagancies, muſt needs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge ſome unjuſt reaſons for what they do, to the great diſparagement and dammage of the Priſoners, whoſe griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances (and what elſe they can ſay for themſelves) cannot be heard, ſo that they are often cenſur'd, even by their beſt Friends, though without any juſt Cauſe, or the leaſt ſhaddow of Truth, contrary to the precepts of true Charity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:132878:5"/>
            <p>Now, leaſt by ſomes neglect in a work you undertook ſo grateful to God, you ſhould looſe any part of your expected Reward from him, I thought it worth my labour, and your knowledge, to give you a particular account of ſome paſſages concerning certain Priſoners, and the mannagers of your Charities. Men and Women while they live in this world have their failings, and where you find either of them to tranſgreſs, be pleaſed in your accuſtomed Bounty, to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial in your Judgments, and let right take place: If you Judge charitably, (as I hope you will) and commiſerate their weakneſs, God will deal with you accordingly, and your works will ſhine on Earth, as it doth in Heaven: In both which places, wiſhes you and yours from his heart, the greateſt Joy and Comfort that can be.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Moſt Vertuous and Pious Ladies,</salute>
               <signed>Your ever obliged, and moſt thankful Servant, Gerard Dowdall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132878:5"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Dowdall</hi>'s JUST and SOBER VINDICATION, <hi>&amp;c. For the Satisfaction of all Impartial CATHOLICKS.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Beloved Friends,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>'TIs no Scandal to the Catholick Religion, to have the Vices of ſome pretended Members thereof diſcovered. The only way to Refine the Church of God, is to ſeparate the good from the Evil; 'tis by that the deſtructive Members are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd from the ſound ones, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the one would corrupt the other, as one ſcabby Sheep doth the whole Flock. The beſt Experienced Artiſts are often deceived in the tryal of Gold by Fire and the Touchſtone,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132878:6"/> the ſame alſo, if it be very good, muſt be malliable, and endure <hi>Aqua fortis:</hi> So it is not a ſufficient motive to believe men true Prieſts or Jeſuits, becauſe they wear Prieſts or Jeſuits habits, and ſay Maſs, ſhewing out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſignes of Devotion (as Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites do) 'Tis therefore neceſſary that their Lives and Converſations witneſs what they pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be, otherwiſe they are to be ſupected as Seducers, and diſturbers of the Peace of honeſt Men; ſuch were ſome Companions of mine in the <hi>Gate-houſe</hi> Priſon of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> although reputed Sufferers for Jeſus Chriſts ſake, when on the contrary, they have practiſed the greateſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice that could be, more becoming Heathens than Chriſtians, more ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Infidels than Catholicks, and much leſs to reputed Prieſts and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, as the impartial Reader may judge by this following diſcourſe.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:132878:6"/>
               <p>Now, that every one may know the neceſſity of this Relation, they muſt yield, that the Laws of God and Nature, obliges every one to defend himſelf, yea, to Kill, rather than be Kill'd: If then it be lawful for every one to defend his Body, much more is it juſt to vindicate his Reputation from Calumnies and Detraction, which renders a man odious to the Word, and in a worſer condition than if he had been quite out of it. I hope then none will be ſcandalized at this my Defence, altho I touch my Adverſaries to the quick, and make them Shamefull to the world, for their little Charity, and great Injuſtice, grounded altogether on Lies, Calumny, and Detraction.</p>
               <p>The firſt grounds of prejudicing me, was a difficulty propounded to me by a Perſon of Quality about ſeven years ago, concerning God and Chriſtian Religion: beſides the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction I gave him then, I directed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132878:7"/> to him one Father <hi>Patuillet,</hi> an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Preacher then in St. <hi>James</hi>'s, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <hi>Don Franciſco di Melos,</hi> the <hi>Portugal</hi> Ambaſſador, and I my ſelf argued the whole matter with a Religious man, a ſtranger then in Town, for to give a greater ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the ſaid Nobleman next time I ſaw him; the aforeſaid ſtranger, as I was inform'd, held a diſpute with an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prieſt to the ſame purpoſe, who afterwards acquainted one <hi>Melchior Power</hi> his Countryman, and a repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prieſt, of what paſs'd; this <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chior</hi> envying my Proſperity, a year before thoſe Troubleſome-times, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures my friends, underhand, that the ſaid Noblemans difficulties, to me propounded, were my own Principles and Opinion, although I never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd with him half a quarter of an hour at once in my life, no, nor ever was under the Roof of an houſe with him that I know, unleſs in a Chappel or this Priſon, and yet by his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132878:7"/> me, I loſt my employment with the Marqueſs of <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> and an expectation of a Preferment by his means, worth one hundred pounds a year, being actually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd therein; and as one Evil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly followeth another, there was no ways to deprive me of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, but by getting the Elector of <hi>Cullens</hi> Reſident to perſwade me his Maſter recall'd me to my former Employments in his Court; after I went thither, I found no ſuch thing; but the Reſident having incurr'd thereby his Highneſs diſpleaſure, was forc'd, in his own defence, to write the whole circumſtance, how he was ſet on: By which Relation (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the greateſt Lie imaginable) the Prince is ſo incens'd againſt me, that I loſt all future expectation in that Court, having formerly had therein two conſiderable Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Reward of which, was uſually a Chanonry of two or three
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132878:8"/> hundred pounds a year during life; I being onely at firſt retyr'd from thence for health ſake. I loſt by this Journey all the Moneys I had, four Suits of Cloaths, and fifteen changes of Linnen, and all my Friends at home and abroad. Afterwards, for a livelyhood, returning to my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, I came to <hi>London,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Melchior Power</hi> was ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful by his calumny, and framed! Lies, in robbing me of all honeſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that among all my former Friends, one onely excepted, I could not obtain ſix pence to bear my charges in the reſt of my Journey; and therefore by tarrying long on the Road for want of Moneys to go with conveniency, I loſt all good op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Wind and Weather, ſo that at laſt theſe troubleſome times ſuddenly coming on, I was taken Priſoner on ſuſpition of being one <hi>Ireland,</hi> a <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Gentleman, and afterwards brought hither to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132878:8"/> 
                  <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> where charitable Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks relieved me bountifully, which the ſaid <hi>Melchior Power,</hi> there alſo in cuſtody, ſuddenly prevented, by relating to other Priſoners, reputed Prieſts and Jeſuits, the former Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny of my Principles and Opinion in matter of Faith, who living alſo on Charity, and therefore as jealous as he of my Gains, joyned with him in confirming the ſame to our Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; upon which falſe Information I loſt them all on a ſudden, ſo that afterwards I ſcarce had a penny from any I ever knew before; inſomuch that thoſe who ſent me word at firſt, they had Gold and Silver at my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, would now have no correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with me, or ſo much as accept my Letters. Among others, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Lady ſent to me, that ſuch a day ſhe would ſend me three Guinnies, the which my Companions under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, preſently got the Lady to be inform'd of their Calumny and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132878:9"/> Lies of me, to which the Lady giving credit, ſent them the three Guinnies, who gave me not one penny thereof. Another Lady I ſerved three years, who hath beſtowed Eighteen pounds on me ſince my Departure from her houſe, underſtanding the ſaid falſe Reports by the ſaid <hi>Melchior Powers</hi> means, would not now in Priſon give me one penny to Relieve me.</p>
               <p>Neither was it to be admir'd, that Strangers flinch'd of, when two Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen of my own Country, and of old acquaintance, with another ſpecial Friend, coming to ſee me, being prepoſſeſt of Mr. <hi>Powers</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, did ſo ſuſpect I ſhould do them a Prejudice, that they ſeemed to tremble in my preſence, ſo that one of them was always ſure to ſtand between me and the Door, leaſt I ſtep'd a ſide to have them apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Thus my Friends being aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from me, the report of my bad Principles and Opinion, in matters of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132878:9"/> Faith, began to die, ſo that at the Years end, there was not a word heard thereof, until the Counteſs of <hi>A.</hi> underſtanding I was the only Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner for Religion that lay on the Boards, offered not only to pay my Chamber Rent while I was to be a Priſoner, but alſo what Debt I owed until then, which ſo gal'd my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, that fearing I was coming again to favour, they put their heads together how to clip my Wings.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that Evening they ſent to me one Mr. <hi>O Cullane,</hi> (who own'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf publickly to be a Prieſt) letting me to underſtand, that he was ſent by the other four of my companions, to acquaint me, how by Writing my neceſſities to Friends abroad, I rob'd them of their ſhares of what I was to have from the aforeſaid Counteſs. I deſir'd him to aſſure them, that in the Faith of a Chriſtian, to the beſt of my Memory, I did not write of my neceſſities to any whatſoever, in a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132878:10"/> quarter of a year at leaſt: That the ſaid Lady was altogether a ſtranger to me, that I never ſent to her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly; that I was then ignorant of her Name and Quality, yet this did not give them any ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, for the Night following, they imployed the ſame Meſſenger, with other Inſtructions to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: At this I was not a little offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, anſwering, that I would diſcourſe the matter before them all: The next day I told them, I was much concern'd at their incredulity, after the Oath I took: That in caſe I ſhould have acquainted ſome abroad of my neceſſities, that would be no unjuſtice done them, being a whole year before deprived of all Relief from former friends, by their calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Lies: That I was indebted for Lodging, and therefore forc'd to lay on the Boards Twenty ſix weeks. That I was credibly inform'd, that one of them got about an hundred
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:132878:10"/> pound gains ſince his Impriſonment: That I ſhould be glad, if he and the reſt had got ten times ſo much. That they alſo ought in Charity to wiſh me well, and not to be ſo incens'd for Gods Providence towards me. But all I ſaid avail'd nothing, for three of them, being chief Leaders, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with a great many Perſons of Quality, eaſily perſwaded the two others to ſide with them: All five unanimouſly, without the leaſt ground of truth, informs the ſaid Counteſs with multitude of Lies of me, and got Mrs. <hi>Catherine Sheldon</hi> to ſecond them; they prevailed ſo far with the ſaid Lady, that ſhe would never afterwards pay one penny of what ſhe promiſed for me. I muſt confeſs, the want of a ſufficient live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood was no ſmall trouble to me in a Priſon, where every thing is ſold at a dear Rate, and where one cannot ſend for the worth of two pence, but muſt pay the Meſſenger, and this out
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132878:11"/> of ſix ſhillings a week, my whole al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance for Meat, Drink, Firing, Candlelight, Waſhing, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of Cloaths, the reſt I give for my Chamber Rent, or elſe I muſt have layn on the Boards in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſide: In truth, all this was the leaſt of my troubles, knowing well, the more my Body ſuffered for Gods ſake, the greater my Reward in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven would be hereafter: the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof, made me rather Glory, then to be any ways troubled at my Impriſonment; but to be back-bited by inhuman Tongues, ſharper than Raizors, who have no more Mercy than the worſt of creatures, perplexes me more, then by any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Art I am able to bear, eſpecially when I conſider, that my Reputation, which I ever prefer'd before all the happineſs of this world, is unjuſtly ſtained by the calumny and malice of the forementioned reputed Prieſts and Jeſuits, who perſecuted me for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132878:11"/> lucre of Monys, and ſelf Intereſt ſake; as the Impartial Reader may judge, ſince they never attempted any thing againſt me, but when they believed I had extraordinary Releif from Friends or was in a likelyhood of obtaining ſome, which hapned to me but twice, to wit at my firſt coming to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as I ſaid before, and a twelve month after when the ſaid Counteſs promiſed to pay my Chamber Rent, the onely two times they vented their Mallice againſt me.</p>
               <p>To prevent for the Future the like abuſes occaſioned by the too much credulitie of the Female Sex, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to Churchmen, or ſo reputed, let them know, that theſe are Men as others are, Subject to all human Frailties, as if they were never ſuch, although by their Profeſſion they ought to overcome their paſſions, but to ſay they all do ſo, is too much preſumption, therefore we muſt yeild ſome bad among them, and every
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132878:12"/> of them to have their impefecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to wit, one has one failing, and another other failings. Who then is of ſo little Sence or Reaſon, as to believe that all theſe Frailties are to be approved off, becauſe committed by ſuch Men? If one of them be Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſelf Intereſted, or Paſſionate, or Revengful, or inclined to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particular Vice, ought we then to ſide with them, and maintain their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe they have other good qualities, as ſome graceleſs Women have done much to my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice: No, God and the Catholick Church hates Vice, and the Uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereof, for certainly 'tis no ſmall Sin to defame unjuſtly a man that bears the Characters of honeſt Principles: I do not doubt but ſuch evil Mouth'd Creatures incurs the wrath of God more then Robbers and Murtheres in the high ways; 'Tis certainly better for one to looſe his Life, then his good Name. My
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132878:12"/> adverſaries by ſtayning my reputation bereived me of my livelyhood, and of all future preferments hereafter: All this while I do not deny but I have been to blame in ſome things; I know being highly provoked, the effect of Paſſion moved me to ſay that which I did not my ſelf approve of ſoon after, for one Mr. <hi>O. Bryan,</hi> (of whom we ſhall ſpeak at large here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) being in great diſtreſs, entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to beg ſome aſſiſtance for him from my Companions, who upon mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, willingly condeſcended, excepting Mr. <hi>Melchior Power,</hi> who anſwered, he needed as much as any in Priſon; I only ſaid, if it was ſo, he was much bely'd, for the common report was, he had Forty Shillings a week ſetl'd on him by four Perſons whom I nam'd to him, as I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, but his anſwer was, I inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame my ſelf, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently I was a Babler. I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I was ſo vex'd thereat, that I did
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132878:13"/> not know whether I ought rather to Bridle my hands more then my tongue, but I did not indeed touch him, although it had been accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deſerts. I own it was my deſtiny to be unjuſtly perſecuted by ſome Churchmen, but that the impartial Reader may be as well a Judge of the occaſion thereof, as my ſelf, I will ſet down ſome Examples.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Mr. <hi>PARSONS.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Second of my Companions in the <hi>Gatehouſe</hi> Priſon who perſecuted me, was one Mr. <hi>Parſons</hi> a reputed Prieſt: This Gentleman ſetting his Paſſion a ſide, is a good natur'd man, but is ſo tranſported with Natural Pride, or rather a Lofty Mind, that he is impoſſible to be pleaſed by ſome, unleſs they yeild wholly to his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors; let others be ever ſo well qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, theſe diſpoſitions I diſcovered in him from the very beginning; and therefore judg'd it moſt neceſſary to comply with him, as with one Born
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132878:13"/> in this Kingdome, and extremaly well beloved, eſpecially by Ladies Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, who commonly brought what Charity we received. 'Tis true indeed, he was a proper handſome man, in the prime of his Age, more agreeable to ſome in his own Perſon, then in that he was reputed to be, which was no ſmall advantage to him in the ſaid diſtribution of Charities.</p>
                  <p>The firſt diſtaſte he took at me, was diſcourſing of ordinary matters, as about the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> and the Cuſtomes, Faſhions, Education, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and common Breeding of all ſorts of People in moſt Countries of <hi>Europe,</hi> in all ſuch occaſions, he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much offended, if contradicted in the leaſt, although I might preſume in ſome difficulties to be his Maſter, I mean as concerning the <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> in which he was altogether ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant; yet he us'd to ſide with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as unknowing as himſelf, againſt me in ſuch Subjects, although I taught
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:132878:14"/> that Science for ſome years; ſo that rather then to hear me prove the matter by clear Demonſtrations, he was wont to fall into a paſſion, calling me a wrangling fellow; but what ever the reaſon was, from that time forward, he boar me an antipathy: he was ſure afterwards, on all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to ſnap and correct me, as if I had been a Boy: I could juſtly ſay, I hardly Din'd five times afterwards in his company without ſome affront: he was not aſham'd to tell me to my face, that I ſeemed never to have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented any Gentlemans company: That I did not know to cut my meat; that he was forc'd to teach me my manners; all that while I never ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any diſpleaſure, but put it off with a Jeſt, onely once I replyed, that it was ſtrange that one who was ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years Governour to Earls, Lords, and Knights Children, and had two conſiderable Imployments in the Prince Elector of <hi>Cullens</hi> Court, did
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132878:14"/> not know how to behave my ſelf in his preſence; beſides, I had my Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation among the beſt Gentry in <hi>Spain, France, Germany,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and more in years then any of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, yet he compacted ſo with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of my Companions, that a whole years time I was forc'd at Meals to ſit at the lower end of their Table; but finding neither there any quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I abſtained wholly from their Dinners, loſing thereby my ſhare of above 40 beſtowed on us in common; at laſt I ſent to him, that ſince I could not eat with him in peace, I ſhould have my ſhare a part, the which he denied for a quarter of a Year, at laſt he ordered me ſome of their Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which I could not eat.</p>
                  <p>All this while he had conſtant viſits from the ſaid Women and others, all which he diſſwaded ſo much from me, that they would not afford me one civil word, ſome attacking me with unbeſeeming Language for concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:132878:15"/> my ſelf with their ordinary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. 'Tis hence to be conjectured what prejudice he has done me in the diſtribution of the Charities, ſince all were delivered, either by his Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, or given him to be devided as he thought fit, although the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Donors were otherwiſe, and that every one ſhould have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his neceſſities and quality, but things were carried on otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>The holy Scriptures aſſures us, that as we treat others, in like manner ſhall we be dealt with alſo. Behold how God has permitted this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, one of the principalleſt Authors of my misfortunes, to be confounded. To defame and prejudice me, he took hold on every groundleſs and ſilly report he heard of me by any ſorry creature whatſoever. Theſe he has ſet forth in the beſt colours he could invent, in confirmation of what he perſwaded folks of me. Afterwards getting out of Priſon on Bayle, he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:132878:15"/> went to one Mr. <hi>Hyens</hi> his houſe in <hi>Hereford-Shire,</hi> whoſe Maid being with Child, declares him to be the Father thereof: And although I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally believe him to be wrongfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, becauſe I hear both he and his Friends recant their raſh Judgments of me heretofore, not doubting, but I was calumniated then, as well as he is now. Yet none can deny, but God afflicts him in the ſame meaſure as he did me: But ſince he ownes his fault, I forgive him, although I ſhall never be able to rub off what preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice I received by his means.</p>
                  <p>It was my general Remark, that whoſoever were his friends (although ever ſo great mine before) became at laſt my Foes, no, nor would they afford me a good look: What Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter then has he given of me, but the worſt that could be? and often in my own preſence, though not hearing, he made his calumny of me a Subject of Laughter to his company. About
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:132878:16"/> this time he procur'd licence to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe daily with other Gentlemen Priſoners on the ſame ſcore in another apartment, call'd, <hi>High-Park,</hi> from ſome of whom, I had ſome times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, but by his going thither, they became as a verſe to me as he, which I learn'd afterwards by woful expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; for having alſo liberty to frequent the ſame place, I renewed my acquaintance with one Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> a reputed Jeſuit, formerly a Schollar in the ſame Colledge I ſtudied in; I offered him all the kindneſs I could expreſs as to one belonging to thoſe places I had part of my Learning and Education from; the which he ſeemed much to ſleight, being already cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Parſons.</hi> The ſecond time he took more notice of me, but the third time I was ſent for to his Chamber by the foreſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, who promiſed (as I ſaid before) to pay my Chamber Rent. She was pleaſed to perſwade me to take my
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:132878:16"/> Lodging among the reſt, until I gave her Ladiſhip reaſons to the contrary, with which ſhe was ſo ſatisfied, that ſhe wiſh'd me agree for my lodging where I pleaſed, and ſhe would ſee it paid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Mr. <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>After her departure, I returned to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Turners</hi> Room, who told me, my diſcourſe with that Lady was not either like that of a Chriſtian, a Gentleman, or a Philoſopher, alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there was no Truth in what I ſaid, and that all the Priſoners could juſtifie the ſame: I anſwered, that I would forfeit my life, if every word I ſaid was not true, to wit, that tho Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber propoſed to me, had a moſt noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſmell, when the wind was on a certain ſide, the which would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice my health. That it would be a great mortification to me, and an hindrance to my Studies, to lay in an open place, the receptacle of all commers and goers. That I naturally delighted to live retiredly. That I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:132878:17"/> was offer'd one of the beſt Rooms in the houſe to me alone for the ſame rate: His anſwer was, I had Maggots in my head; that I was totter-headed, with other reproachful words: and to be brief, he told me, if I did not remove willingly to the place the Lady mentioned at firſt, I ſhould be hal'd thither: I deſired to know for what, which he ſaid was not expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to tell me, and therefore I muſt reſolve to concur. I reply'd, that I never made profeſſion in any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Order, and conſequently was not tied to the Vows of obedience. That by his diſcourſe I conceived there was ſome evil aſperſion caſt on me; that it behoved me to clear my ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of before I removed, leaſt by conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending firſt to their demands, I ſeemed to the world, I own'd my ſelf guilty of I know not what. That I was the oldeſt of all the company, excepting himſelf: That I was come to years to know my own conveniency
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:132878:17"/> better than any of them could direct me. I preſs'd both him then, and the reſt afterwards, to let me know what they had to ſay againſt me, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, that if I did not clear my ſelf of what ever was to be laid to my charge, I would ſubmit to what they pleaſed, and beg them pardon on my knees for my reſiſtance, they all anſwered, both generally and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, they had nothing to ſay againſt me.</p>
                  <p>Why then have I been mangled and torn alive in a thouſand pieces a whole years time, by the venemous Tongues of ſo ſhameleſs a Generation of men? who by the ſame mouths uttered hundreds of calumnies againſt me in private, now to my face pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly diſowns the ſame. Where are thoſe Proſelites whom they have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to aggravate their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all the Kingdom over? Behold the Knavery of thoſe you honoured ſo highly, and lov'd ſo dearly: You
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:132878:18"/> have ſided with their Iniquity, and alſo juſtified their Calumnies with flouriſhes of hundred lies, which God will never forgive you without reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution to me firſt of my Reputation.</p>
                  <p>To proceed further in the Mallice of my Companions, the aforeſaid Counteſs, according to her promiſe, came with the Moneys I was to have for diſcharging my debt in Priſon, but the Gentlemen, notwithſtanding they aſſured me they had nothing to ſay of me, as I declar'd before, yet they gave ſuch a bad character to the Lady of me, that they cauſed her to carry back the Moneys again, alleadging that it was firſt neceſſary I remove my Lodging to the foreſaid ſtinking Room; on this reſolution they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed Mrs. <hi>Catherine Sheldon</hi> thrice to me in an hours time, to let me know what was concluded; I told her, if the occaſion of my removal was the flying reports ſpread of me by my Companions, it behoved me to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:132878:18"/> juſtifie my ſelf, leaſt by complying to their humours, I might give occaſion to the world to think me guilty of their falſe aſperſions. That if it was to the end we might live all together, I would condeſcend to remove in an hours warning. The third time I ſaid I would yield to what ſhe pleaſed; with this ſhe brought the foreſaid Counteſs with Moneys for me, which ſhe gave Mr. <hi>Church</hi> our head Goaler, aſſuring him, in the preſence of four more, ſhe would pay my Chamber Rent for the future while I was to be a Priſoner. The ſame day I removed my things to the place appointed, thinking to lodge there that Night: No ſooner did I get among them, but I found it was not my company they look'd for, nor any thing elſe but a pretence to hinder me of the Ladies favours; ſo that on a ſudden they ſet Nic-names on me, making me alſo believe Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> would ſpeak with me, when at the ſame time he was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:132878:19"/> aſleep, and had not asked for me. Forthwith I concluded it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for me to enjoy peace among thoſe that deſigned to croſs and abuſe me, therefore I reſolv'd to tarry where I was: Yet converſing with them daily in the common Room, when there was no offenſive ſmell, I was no ſmall Paſtime to Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> for ſome days; who finding no other object of his Jeſts but me, made uſe of my Name above forty times in each hour; adding, that Women in <hi>England</hi> that never left their Chimny-corner, ſpoke better than I do after all my Travels. That none in the houſe were ſuch great Hoggs in their Cloaths as he and I: That the reſt were well vers'd in Philoſophy and Divinity, but he and I were the onely moams in the Priſon, with an hundred other like ſour Jeſts: But in this we were ill met, for altho I forbore with his doings for quietneſs ſake, yet I thought often I never met with ſo undiſcreet a man of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:132878:19"/> before; I wonder'd at the Mans little prudence, or rather great impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to preſs familiarity on one that never ſpent an hour in Recreation with him in my life time. I could not imagin wherein a man I knew to be of no Parts, no Traveller, no Linguiſt, no Hiſtorian; and ſcarce worth the Name of a Schollar, ſhould ground ſuch confidence, for Lattin he durſt not ſpeak, the Mathematicks he knew not, and for any other knowledge, I am ſure he has but little. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on a Pious matter ſome Latin Verſes, wherein I left on purpoſe ſome notable faults, to ſee his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; but his opinion was, they were all very good, much admiring I could make them without the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Books.</p>
                  <p>To be brief, when I found at laſt no end of his inſolent Jeſts, I ſpoke to him one day in a very moderate manner, telling him, I admired at his little wiſdom, in breaking his Jeſts
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:132878:20"/> on one of my Age and calling, as if I were not <hi>compos Mentis.</hi> That if he did but reflect on himſelf, he would find Beams in his own Eyes, for the Mors he perceived in mine: at which he ſtarted, ſuddenly asking, how's that? I told him ingeniouſly, without the leaſt ſign of Paſſion, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time I enter'd his Chamber, I took notice, that it was his diſorderly drinking occaſioned his tedious Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which was enough to kill a Hogg; for in the Morning faſting, he call'd firſt for a Glaſs of Canary, next a Glaſs of Rheniſh Wine, after that a Glaſs of Claret, all which overheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Stomach, he call'd at laſt for a Glaſs of Beer, a Medicine indeed that would Kill me in one Months time; hereat he retir'd to his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, two days after he ſent to me the forementioned Mr. <hi>Cullane,</hi> adviſing me to ask him pardon on my knees, and to tell the ſtanders by, what I ſaid to him were Lies, or elſe he would
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:132878:20"/> write to all my Benefactors, not to ſend me a penny Relief. I anſwered, ſure Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> is in his Jeſting hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours again, and ſo took no further notice of it. The next day he deſir'd one Mr. <hi>Maccarty,</hi> now condemn'd for a Prieſt in <hi>Newgate,</hi> to bring me the ſame Meſſage: I anſwered, ſince he is in earneſt, I will ſpeak to him, ſo going to his room, I ſaid, Mr. <hi>Turner,</hi> why would you ſend me ſuch Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for a thing I did not offend God venially, and although I ſaid nothing but the Truth, yet I concern'd my ſelf in that ſame againſt my inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, only to divert you from making me the Subject of your Laughter. Then he replyed, Mr. <hi>Dowdall,</hi> you ſtand to what you ſaid, I adviſe you to ask me Pardon on your knees, and to declare openly, what you ſaid of my Drinking was falſe, or elſe I will write to all your friends not to ſend you a penny maintenance. I ask'd him, if he would have me tell a Lye,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:132878:21"/> or if he thought the world was to be rul'd by one Jeſuit, and ſo departed; but my Gentleman was as good as his word, for ever after I ſcarce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any aſſiſtance towards my livelyhood, but what one Lady ſent me weekly, whom he endeavoured to diſſwade alſo from Relieving me.</p>
                  <p>Now to accompliſh his deſign the better, he made uſe (among others) of the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Catherine Sheldon,</hi> one of the beſt Friends I had before, as I own'd it to her and her Siſters by two or three Letters I writ to them; on ſuſpition had of their diſpleaſure with me, but the inſtructions of Mr. <hi>Turner,</hi> and my other companions, wrought ſo much on the former, that my Letters (although the moſt oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I could Pen) were not accepted as good enough for waſte papers; ſo that ſhe did not only retract from me the uſual Charities given her by others as well for me, as any elſe; but thence forth made it her buſineſs to do me
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:132878:21"/> all the prejudice immaginable, as if ſhe was the chief party concerned; altho ſhe her ſelf cannot tell what I did to diſoblige her, unleſs ſhe took a pett I did not remove my Lodging when my Companions would have me. Yet ſhe cauſed the foreſaid Counteſs, that promiſed to pay ſo ſolemnly my Chamber Rent, not to give me one penny ever after. I may dare lay there is no Catholick Lady of any Quality in <hi>London,</hi> whom ſhe did not, either by her ſelf or by others, incenſe againſt me.</p>
                  <p>Once a certain Lady of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance ſent her five Guinnies to be given me, and having ſoon after writ again to the ſaid Lady for ſome aſſiſtance, towards my Bayling forth, ſhe ſent to me her Woman, to know whether I did not receive the ſaid five Guinnies from Mrs. <hi>Catherine Sheldon,</hi> I anſwered, not a penny, and while the ſaid Lady ſent me ſome more Relief, the ſaid Mrs. <hi>C. S.</hi> or her Siſter,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:132878:22"/> went to her, rayling at me in ſuch a manner, that the Lady ſaid, ſhe wiſh'd ſhe had thrown her moneys in the <hi>Thames,</hi> before ſhe ſent it me. One of her objections was, that I fiddle faddle my moneys away, becauſe I gave 50 ſhillings for a Morning Gown I wore inſtead of Cloaths I wanted, but ſhe thought ſo much monys well ſpent by one of my Companions; ſhe wiſh'd well for a Silk flower'd Waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat, although he was but a Serving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Son, and that my Father has had a conſiderable Eſtate.</p>
                  <p>Neither was ſhe ſatisfyed to make what uſe ſhe could of her own tongue, but imployed her Siſter <hi>Francis,</hi> Maid of Honour, who was altogether a ſtranger to me, to incenſe the Q and her R. H. againſt me, to the one I was recommended by a ſpecial Letter from the Prince Elector of <hi>Cullen,</hi> my former Maſter, and to the other by the Marqueſs of <hi>Mountecuculi,</hi> Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Duke of <hi>Modena.</hi> All
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:132878:22"/> this while I knew no better Remedy, than to take a Hair of the ſame Dog that bit me. I therefore applied my ſelf again to Mr. <hi>Turner,</hi> declaring, that if he did not Reconcile ſuch Friends as he alienated from me, to me again, I would complain of his Injuſtice, to others of the Society.</p>
                  <p>Before I ſent away either of the two Letters I writ to that purpoſe, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him therewith, deſiring we might be Friends, which he rejected, ſaying, <hi>Do your worſt;</hi> but imagining him to be in a paſſion, I kept one of the ſaid Letters in my Chamber about three weeks, and the other near ſix, preſſing him alſo by others to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation: Then indeed he ſeemed to be ſo well ſatisfied with the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation given him by one Mr. <hi>Parſons</hi> an Inferior Officer in Priſon, of the Injuries done me by the Lies of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious perſons, that he ſaid, <hi>He would never give credit to any evil ſaid of me any more;</hi> yet afterwards, when Mrs.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:132878:23"/> 
                     <hi>Catherine Sheldon</hi> aſſur'd me, that if my Companions would give it under their hands, that they were ſatisfied, I ſhould Lodge where ever I pleaſed; ſhe would procure the ſaid Counteſs to pay my Chamber Rent, according to promiſe. Whereupon I writ this preſent Certificate in their Names.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We whoſe Names hereunder Written, do think it moſt juſt and reaſonable, that Mr.</hi> Dowdall <hi>layeth in what Room ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Mr.</hi> Church <hi>our Goaler affords him for his better convenience.</hi> And although I added underneath, that by ſubſcribing to this, all our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences would be at an end, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, I ſhould be again forc'd to lay on the Boards, yet Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> and Mr. <hi>Parſons,</hi> denied to ſet their hands to it, without giving me any reaſon thereof, onely Mr. <hi>Parſons</hi> ſaid to his Nameſake the Turn-key, that by thus ſubſcribing, all the blame of our dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences would be laid on them.</p>
                  <p>Let then any indifferent Perſon be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:132878:23"/> judge, if this be a Chriſtian like anſwer; do not we know that a Sin is never forgiven without reſtitution of Honor and Goods, if it be in our power. Are thoſe fit to guide other Mens Souls that maintain and practiſe ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Principles? They Perſecute the Innocent, they rob him of his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Livelyhood, and yet at no times will they do him Juſtice, leaſt themſelves be found guilty of an Errour.</p>
                  <p>But why do I wonder at thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings? when I often ſaid, that in all my Travels, in moſt Kingdoms of <hi>Europe,</hi> I never was Eye-witneſs to more tricks and knavery then I have ſeen practiſed by the forenamed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of mine in this Priſon, altho reputed Prieſts and Jeſuits. I often ſaid, if I knew no more of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity then I learned from them, I would chooſe rather to be a <hi>Turk</hi> than a <hi>Catholick.</hi> I alwayes compared them to ſo many <hi>Mountebanks</hi> in a Market
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:132878:24"/> place, where each one makes the beſt of his Druggs: how jealous then may we juſtly ſuppoſe is each one of the others gains? Even ſo were my five Companions, or rather Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, concern'd at the diſtribution of Charities, when Ladies, or their Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, frequented more one than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but with this diſtinction, that the <hi>Mountebancks</hi> have more Grace than to defame one anothers Credit or Reputation, although they may exclaim at each others Druggs: But my Companions made it their whole buſineſs, to Defame, Back-bite, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, and Calumniate each other, drawing thereby all the profit to themſelves. There was one of them ſo ingenious, that whilſt he and I walk'd in a certain Room, a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman call'd (to my hearing) for my Name, but he being next the door, ſaid to her, Madam, I am alſo on the ſame ſcore, will you pleaſe ſit down, and although I told him in another
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:132878:24"/> Language, I heard her call for me, he anſwered, I will tell you another time; but then he plaid his part ſo well, that in my own preſence, he got the Moneys brought for me. He was indeed a pretty young man, but let me tell you, no <hi>Mountebanck</hi> could deal more cunningly. I could have eaſily forgiven him and the reſt ſuch ſmall faults as this, or any Money buſineſs, if they did not prejudice my Reputation and good Name: They knew well there was but little to be done, unleſs I was quite out of favour, which could only be, by giving very bad Characters of me. In this Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> was a very great Inſtrument: Among other Lies divulg'd of me, he affirms, that when I went to School at <hi>Liege,</hi> I had my Diet at Citizens houſes for Charity, when I take God to witneſs, I never eat or drunk with any of them, no, not upon any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whatſoever, to the beſt of my memory, but what I or my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:132878:25"/> paid for. He alſo ſaith, he gave ten ſhillings to one of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety for me. I own I got ſome monys from one of them, for coppying two Books in vacant times, which I earn'd well, without any obligation to him, a man I never ſpoke a word to, but in this Priſon. There was lately in this Kingdome, one of that Colledge that boarded in the ſame houſe I did, who can teſtifie, that there were not three of twelve <hi>Engliſh</hi> boarders then in that Town that had better Meat, Drink, and Lodging, then I have had, and yet I muſt be calumniated to my face by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Turner.</hi> It ſeems he makes no ſcruple in ſuch things, for one day diſcourſing of a certaine matter, I might lawfully Swear, he told a dozen Lies, and the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, he abſolutely deny'd he ever ſaid any ſuch thing; you may gueſs his little Conſcience by this. A certain Gentlewoman having moneys to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow among thoſe that were moſt in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:132878:25"/> want in the Priſon, addreſſing her ſelf to the before named <hi>Melchior Power,</hi> who it ſeems told her, that Mr. <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> had what moneys he wanted from his own friends, at which he was ſo incens'd againſt the ſaid <hi>Power,</hi> that he ſaid to one Mr. <hi>B.</hi> a Priſoner, that he would never have any Charity or kindneſs for him: Whoſoever deſires to be further inform'd of him, let them but enquire his manner of life in <hi>Derby-Shire,</hi> and they will be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfied, although ſome certain Women here in Town now honours him as an Oracle; who much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me, that when he removed from this Priſon, to the Maſters own houſe, I refuſed to approach him, never conſidering, that his pretence of taking leave with me then, was onely a fained Complement; he hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a whole quarter of a year before rejected all propoſalls of a Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, or any ſatisfaction of Honour or Damages. If they had but the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:132878:26"/> diſcretion after hearing one party, to give ear to the other, certainly I could not be ſo abus'd as I was. In this a certaine Gentleman, that brought me the only allowance I had for my livelihood, behav'd himſelf wiſely, for after Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> made uſe of all the arguments he could invent, to have this ſame Charity taken from me, the ſaid Gentleman deſired to hear what I could ſay in my own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, which ſo confounded all the former Calumny, that he ſeemed to be much ſcandaliz'd thereat, ſaying to me afterwards, muſt we for trifles ſeek anothers deſtruction, and defraud him of his Livelyhood?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Mr. <hi>THORNE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>But while I was clearing my ſelf, one <hi>Thomas Thorne</hi> a Catholick, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore both Groom and Butler to a Gentleman in the Country, and then a Priſoner for Treaſonable words, was extream inſolent in his diſcourſe to me, denying alſo that he told me what
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:132878:26"/> moneys Mr. <hi>Parſons</hi> got in Priſon, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I took God to witneſs ſeveral times, he aſſured me that great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities were brought to Priſon, and detained by ſome particulars, that he himſelf ſaw with Mr. <hi>Parſons</hi> in one paper Twenty five Guinnies, and in another Thirty four or Thirty five Broad pieces, beſides ſeveral heaps of Silver, carried away by his Siſter the Shoomakers Widdow; all which the ſaid <hi>Thorne</hi> denying, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by an Oath on the Bible, that he told me ſo, but whether he ſaid true, I did not know: This fellow likewiſe took his Oath on the ſame Bible, he told me no ſuch thing, treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me beſides with very uncivil Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; and the more I wiſh'd him to be quiet, the more impertinent he was: I roſe up with an intention to box him, but Mr. <hi>Parſons</hi> being in the way, held me in his Armes, which the ſaid fellow perceiving, and that one hand could not aſſiſt the other,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:132878:27"/> moſt treacherouſly gave a ſnak at my little finger, and turn'd it quite back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the uſe of which, I am like never to enjoy: I would not have blamed him to uſe me worſe in his own defence, had I but once touch'd him. This fellow at his firſt coming to Priſon, was counted an harmleſs Fool, but before his departure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a cunning Knave, and as greedy of gathering moneys, as a Hawk is at his Prey. I could declare ſome other notorious and unheard of miſdemean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours he committed in Priſon, but I judg it a ſubject not worth my labour.</p>
                  <p>I beſeech all good Catholicks to take notice, that this Fellow hath ever ſince boar me ſo great a ſpleen, that he makes it his buſineſs, being now at Liberty, to invent moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Lies of me, without any cauſe, or the leaſt ſhadow of truth, as God of Heaven is my witneſs; yet I do not at all think ſtrange, if ſuch an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant fellow as he is, ſhould do worſe,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:132878:27"/> being inſtructed a whole year in the like practiſes, by ſuch as by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ought to do well. Happy then are they that are born of Honourable Parents, whoſe Sons would ſcorn to be Authors of ſuch ſhameful doings, as my companions practiſed againſt me, for the ſake of ſuch inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able gains; contrariwiſe, the beſt of theſe, I believe, never ſaw better days then in Priſon; Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> is known to be a Miniſters Son, Mr. <hi>Parſons</hi>'s Father was onely Servant to a Lord, Mr. <hi>Power</hi> was a common Souldier in <hi>France,</hi> and at <hi>London,</hi> and ſo ſilly a one, that a Souldier that went to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him, finding him a Sleep at his Sentry, perſwaded him that one of the great Guns was ſtoln, which as is ſaid, <hi>Power</hi> apprehending a great deal of danger he was in, gave the other Souldier mony to be Silent.</p>
                  <p>The two others were ſtrangers in the Kingdom, and oppos'd me, as I ſuppoſe, only to comply with the reſt,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:132878:28"/> both of them of a moſt obſcure gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which one comprehending, and believing himſelf more obliged to Nature then to his Birth, borrowed ſo much credit of his Neighbours, as to make himſelf not a little look'd on.</p>
                  <p>Now that the Reader may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that others (as well as thoſe already mentioned) have the like fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, I will add ſome few Examples. At my firſt coming to <hi>London</hi> from his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Cullens</hi> Court, I undertook a preferment at the <hi>Venetian</hi> Ambaſſadors, I being well vers'd in his Language: who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſuddenly entertained me, which four or five Fryars of that Family envying, went thrice againſt me to have me out of my imployment; The Ambaſſador acquainted me therewith, alſo asking what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar knowledge I had with them, and how long, I told him, I was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three weeks in Town, all which time I never was in either of their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:132878:28"/> Companys, nor did I believe they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw me but in his houſe, yet ſaid he, they bear you mallice, but you ſhall not fare the worſe for that, contrarywiſe, you ſhall have Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over them whilſt they depend on me.</p>
                  <p>When theſe could not prevail with the Ambaſſador, they imployed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their own profeſſion to one Doctor <hi>Warren</hi> a very honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who alone was to give Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my good behaviour while I was in Town, being a ſtranger to all the reſt; deſiring him not to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance me, but rather to have me out of Town, as he told me afterwards; Adding alſo, how he enquir'd what they had to alleadge againſt me, and that they replyed, I was a ſtranger to them, and therefore not fit to be prefer'd in ſuch conſiderable Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as I enjoyed: ſome years after I hapned to be a Governour to a Young Lord, which alſo gal'd them
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:132878:29"/> much, for one of them acquainted my Lord <hi>Almonor</hi> of an Arch-Lie, to wit, I left the Maid of the houſe I lived in with Child, uppon which the ſaid <hi>L. A.</hi> went ſtraight ways to my Young Lords Mother, deſiring her Ladiſhip to Baniſh me out of her houſe for the reaſons aforeſaid. The Lady admiring that he ſhould know the concerns of her houſe better then her ſelf, preſently examin'd the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and found that his Lordſhip was as guilty as I was of what he ſaid, and that the Maids ſhe then had, were never ſuſpected before of any diſhoneſty: I deſir'd reparation of honour and good name of my Lord, but he beg'd my pardon, aſſuring me he would never any more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſtories of me, being twice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore guilty of wronging me, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering his own Friends to my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, for which he was once check'd by the <hi>Q.</hi> but he came off as ill as he begun, declaring I had
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:132878:29"/> dependancy of a Lady of ill repute, yet his Lordſhip prefer'd one of his beſt Friends to ſuch an other prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with a Lady of a far worſe report.</p>
                  <p>I could mention many other like Examples, touching my ſelf, which I leave out for Brevities ſake. Let us then conclude with the Scriptures, that whoſoever thinks himſelf no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, is a Lyar: If therefore all men be breakers of Gods holy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſince the juſt offends him ſeven times a day, why then ſhould any juſtifie them in their evils? as many tatling Women publickly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd what Calumnie ſoever my Companions reported of me, out of ſome Natural kindneſs, or ſome good opinion they conceived of them. I know love and hatred perverts moſt Men and Womens judgment; I know the love ſome of the ſaid Women boar to my Adverſaries, and the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred they conceived of me for their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:132878:30"/> ſakes, made them do me all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice immaginable; and now I am forc'd to ſtoop under the weight of ſo great a burden, languiſhing for the wounds their Lies and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies gave to my Reputation; the which I ever prefer'd before my Life, wiſhing rather to dye, then to be defil'd.</p>
                  <p>Some judicious men underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how many Rivalls I have had at all times, (began as they told me) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to conclude among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that ſurely I muſt be a man of great parts that was ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed; as if one of little capacity would not be regarded or taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, much leſs fit to be prefer'd before them; I only told them in my own behalf, that I would undertake to teach Mr. <hi>Power</hi> and another of my Adverſaries, as yet two years their Lattin, and to inſtruct all the five in the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> and in three Forreign Languages, yet they were
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:132878:30"/> to me as ſo many Doggs in a Manger, neither minding themſelves of any Studies all the year long, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting me to divert my ſelf according to my inclinations therein; having before I was croſs'd and tormented by them, compos'd three Books in Priſon, one of <hi>Heraldry,</hi> another of the <hi>Mathematicks</hi> and the third a <hi>Hiſtory Book,</hi> notwithſtanding it was reſolved, unleſs I forſook all conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of Studies, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul'd, or rather led by the Noſe by them, I ſhould be depriv'd of the payment of my Chamber-Rent, and looſe my ſhare of the Charities ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered for Priſoners; all which was afterwards punctually obſerv'd by calumniating and belieying me all the City and Country over.</p>
                  <p>The Reaſon I have ſo often accus'd them of Lies, is, becauſe if they told but truth, they could do me no harm. They are alſo guilty of Calumny, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, and Back-biting, although
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:132878:31"/> what they invented of me was true, becauſe none can diſcover another Mans crimes, unleſs publickly known without a Mortal ſin; for the holy Scripture ſaith, <hi>If your Brother or Neighbour offend you, admoniſh him of his faults between him and you pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately; if he amends not, correct him before Witneſſes; if he rejects alſo this, complain of him to the Church, or his Superiors; if then he is not Penitent, let him be to you as a Reprobate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not one of my Companions follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Precept, although I put them in mind thereof, begging for Gods ſake they would tell me what it was they heard or believed of me; each of them anſwered, as I ſaid before, <hi>Nothing;</hi> upon this I intreated a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Lady of Quality to reconcile me to the foreſaid Counteſs, but ſhe ſent to me, that nothing could be done; for the five reputed Prieſts and Jeſuits (my companions) had given ſo bad a Character of me, that ſhe was wholly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:132878:31"/> incens'd againſt me. 'Tis true indeed, before this honourable Counteſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to pay my Chamber Rent, I lay on a Quilt on the Boards, but with this ſatisfaction, that the Maſter of the Priſon knowing my little ability, ſaid he would be ſatisfied with eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen pence a week; but the ſaid Counteſs having promiſed him the payment of my Chamber Rent, in what Room ſoever I lay, I am ever ſince ingaged in five ſhillings a week, without any likelihood of payment, or to have the advantage of my ſaid Quilt on the Boards without three and ſix pence a week; ſo that the promiſe of the ſaid Lady, is no ſmall prejudice to me: All which is contrary to the good opinion I had of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, whom I have heretofore extol'd above all others I knew, both for their Piety, Charity, and good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, eſpecially in theſe times of Troubles, which I really believ'd were ſufficient motives to appeaſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:132878:32"/> Wrath, and manyfold afflictions they lay under. But now, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction can I make of theſe prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vertues, when on a ſudden I ſee them decline their good Principles, as if not well grounded therein.</p>
                  <p>I ſent to ſome Ladies of Quality, a brief account of the former tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions againſt me, the which they did reject with a great deal of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and unbecoming Language, not believing one word I writ. One was ſo offended with my defence, that ſhe ſent my Letter open to me back again, but ſeeing there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therein but what concern'd me to let all Catholicks know; therefore I directed her Ladiſhips Letter to her Butler and Cook-Maid, deſiring them to let others, their fellow Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, know the Contents thereof, and how the Unjuſtice of my Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were countenanced by moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in Town.</p>
                  <p>How then can they expect that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:132878:32"/> God will hear their complaints and grievances in the times of Sorrow, ſince they are Upholders of Injuſtice and Wickedneſs themſelves. They pretend to be much injur'd by the falſe accuſations of their ill Wiſhers, and yet make no ſcruple to juſtifie the Calumny maintain'd againſt their Brother. They blame their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours for giving credit to the falſe Reports of their Enemies, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are as willing to believe for Truth, any Lies invented againſt him, whom God and the World knows to be Innocent in what he is accus'd. They ſeem to have Faith, that God will confound the firſt Authors of their Sufferings, but do not think it Damnation to themſelves to Rob an other of his good Name and Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                  <p>For my part, I commiſerate the weakneſs of theſe Catholicks, who think it lawful to do any thing which Church-men perſwades them. Yet
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:132878:33"/> I am rather of opinion, that they are led by ſome natural kindneſs, or ſome other Intereſt, or elſe they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſo blinded, as to prejudice him that never did them the leaſt diskindneſs, either in thought, word, or deed. Now I begin to conſider, that one of the Gentlewomen that oppos'd me ſo highly in a thing which did not concern her at all, was ſo paſſionately in Love with one of my Adverſaries, that whenſoever he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, her countenance chang'd into divers colours, uſing Congies more becoming a Court then a Priſon, and much leſs to a reputed Prieſt. I wiſh they were both where they liſted, an hundred Miles off, and that I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen either of their faces. I am the more confirm'd in this opinion, by a late example of a certain Widow who contracted extraordinary friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with one of our fellow Priſoners for Religion, and who beſtowed on me alſo part of the Charities ſhe ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:132878:33"/> but her friend underſtanding I was much offended with him for writing underhand to Mrs. <hi>Catherine Sheldon,</hi> ſomething to my prejudice, as I believe, onely to curry favour with her, he and I being intimate friends, declared to the ſaid Widdow the diſpleaſure he conceived of me, by which I am ſure to looſe her friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for the future, having thereby already loſt twice or thrice my ſhare of the Charities ſhe collected. I know from an Eye-witneſs how their inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy is grounded, but I will omit that, and ſuch like cauſes of my ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, as not becoming Cage or Goal-Birds (as we are) to foul their own Neſts. This I aſſert for Truth, there was not one Saint among them, and that each of their failings did ballance what ever they could juſtly accuſe me of from firſt to laſt.</p>
                  <p>'Tis with me as with a great many, who fare worſe by looking over a Hedge, then others do by ſtealing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:132878:34"/> either Horſe or Mare: I have been from a Child as ſober as any could be, being never once half fudled in my life time. All that knows me can witneſs, I never drink but when I eat. I never was enclin'd to Swearing, Curſing, or Wrangling; but ſo far from that, that I naturally delighted in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarineſs, inſomuch, that very ſeldom I walk'd with a companion, or was ſeen in an Ale houſe, Tavern, nor at a Club above thrice as yet; having never taken either Snuff or Tobacco; when I am in my Chamber, I muſt be imploy'd in ſomething. It was always natural to me, to do as I would be done unto; yea, to ſerve others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of true Charity, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an hundred times, out of a natural pity, given to the needy what I wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for my ſelf. I eſteemed it cruelty to deny my good word or labour, where I could ſerve my Neighbour. I could have counted once Forty that liv'd by my Recommendation, when
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:132878:34"/> I inſtructed Gentlemens Sons in their houſes; and now I cannot find one to go in an Arrand for me. I had ſuch an abhorrence for Lying, that I never eſteemed ſo much any ones Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as to tell a Lye to gain his favour, or to ſhun his diſpleaſure; eſteeming thoſe that are ſubject thereunto, not fit for Human converſation. Honeſt and Juſt dealing, was a natural Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in me, never deſiring in buying the Seller ſhould looſe his gains. I ever fancied to pay my Creditors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I went to Bed, when I had it, as every one that knows me can teſtifie. I prefer'd a good Repute before any worldly happineſs, in order thereunto, I kept no company but thoſe who were fit for the beſt ſort of Gentry. Perhaps in this I was ſomewhat too ſhie or nice, for which I got ill will, eſpecially when I lived in Families, where I never eat at any ones ſecond Table, unleſs in the Prince of <hi>Cullens</hi> Court, where all Noblemens Sons
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:132878:35"/> were my Companions, and that eight of his Highneſſes Livery men were to wait daily on us at Meals. As for my inward Conſcience, I leave that to be decided by God alone. This I know, if I diſſembled and play'd the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, as ſome of my companions did, I ſhould have a hundred times more Moneys and Credit than I have; moſt of my Companions being famous in both, could act what they liſted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceptions.</p>
                  <p>Each of them could with Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity Nobly Treat one Young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or other, of very ill repute, all day long in their Rooms: It was not worth taking Notice of, if one of them ſent for more Bottles of Wine and Brandy in one day, then I drank Beer or Ale in a whole Week: Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them might lawfully call two or three of their young Devotes, their Wives, and as many more their Miſſes, who uſed to call them Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Gallants in like manner;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:132878:35"/> the reſt of the young Women muſt be their Siſters, and ſuch as were elderly their Mothers. Yes, our holy Patriarck Mr. <hi>Power</hi> himſelf took the Liberty to look himſelf up dayly in his Chamber for ſome hours with a young Woman he pretended to be his Neece, although a condemn'd Prieſt in <hi>Newgate,</hi> his own Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man has openly aſſur'd there is no ſuch Relation between them. A Gentleman of good Credit did aſſure me that one of the Women this God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man us'd to have commonly look'd up in his Chamber, boar a Baſtard to one of his acquaintance, who kept her for his Miſs ſome years. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this while I do not accuſe either him or the reſt of any evil, although they defam'd me pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly without quarter ſuch occaſions given; one would think that thoſe who took ſuch Liberty themſelves, ought to be the more indulgent in cenſuring others: But what can be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:132878:36"/> expected from People of no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but cruelty: they made a God of their pleaſures, the which they knew they could not enjoy without Moneys, and therefore they reſolv'd to have my ſhare between them, which would be conſiderable, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my great acquaintance in Town: And becauſe, in my Paſſion, I threatned to bring them and their Calumny to queſtion, nothing muſt ſatisfie them but my Life, or a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Impriſonment; as it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in this following Treatiſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:132878:36"/>
               <head>The Second Chapter. How my Companions endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Bereave me of my life.</head>
               <p>'TIs a general Remark throughout the World, that the worſt of Men, are thoſe who formerly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vertuous Principles, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards decline from the ſame; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is very plain, for ſome are Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſo proud, and have ſo good an opinion of themſelves, that they ſcarce give glory to God for the graces they receive, as if all the good Deeds they did, were properly attributed to themſelves; and therefore in place of pittying their Neighbours failings, or giving thanks to God, that they were not ſo deſtitute of his graces and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours as they, they ſcoff at their weakneſs, cenſuring them often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:132878:37"/> their Deſarts, when in Charity they ought to Pray for their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. By this preſumption, and other faults annexed thereunto, they incur God's diſpleaſure; and thus looſing part of the ſuperabundant graces they enjoyed before, preſently they fall from one ſin to another, until at laſt, God leaves them wholly to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and then being deſtitute of all grace, they plung into all manner of Vice, not unlike to a Thunderbolt, devouring where ever it comes. Thus by Pride and Preſumption, the bad Angels were thrown out of Paradice, and becoming Devils, are made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to puniſh the Offenders of Gods holy Laws.</p>
               <p>I know none more fit to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to them, then my forementioned five Companions; their Education doubtleſs was Vertuous, their Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing could not be otherwiſe, they being inſtructed as Schollars, and received (as is ſuppoſed) to Dignity, which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:132878:37"/> did ſo puff them up with Pride and Preſumption, that they forgot not onely the former Slavery of their Birth-right, but alſo to render God thanks for their preſent condition. God then having abandoned them, there is no Evil but they are ready to embrace: Behold then how they aime at my Life, for ſaying, <hi>I would Proſecute ſome of them to the utmoſt of the Law, unleſs they gave me ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for what Injuries they did me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor was Satan wanting to their endeavours; for a certain Woman I kept in Priſon from Starving, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with her Sucking-Child, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Liberty, beg'd me for God's ſake, to continue my Charity, until ſhe and her Sick Husband recruited themſelves of their loſſes and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages; I told her, when ſhe or her children wanted Bread at home, they ſhould, as formerly, have a ſhare of my Dinner: her eldeſt Daughter, about Eight years old, I ſent with my
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:132878:38"/> Arrants, until at laſt, I took notice of her growing too confident among the Priſoners, throwing ones Hat, and anothers Periwig off, and that I could not get her away when I deſir'd it, always pretending, ſhe durſt not go home, without bringing ſomething to her Mother: upon which, I warn'd her ſaid Mother, in preſence of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, to keep her Daughter at home, which being ſome hindrance to her, doubtleſs provoak'd her to do me what prejudice ſhe could, unleſs I preſented her with ſome Moneys. There paſs'd ſeven or eight weeks without any diſturbance, until at laſt ſhe heard I was to be Bayl'd out, ſo that very day I was to give Bayle at a Judges houſe, ſhe ſent her ſaid Daughter a purpoſe to Trapan me, whom I met as I was going forth, I ſaid only to her, I am going abroad, I cannot ſpeak to you now. From this day forth, until about three weeks after, ſhe never came to my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:132878:38"/> alone: That day being <hi>Munday,</hi> ſhe told me they wanted Bread at home, and that her Mother wiſh'd her to come to me, that ſhe might not alſo go faſting to School in the Afternoon: I gave her the remainder of my Dinner and a penny, wiſhing her to call me a Neighbour ſhe knew, without expecting to ſee her any more, but within an hour after, I met her in the paſſage to my Chamber, letting me know, that the Woman I ſent for, went away by Night, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Key under the door, enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring beſides (laughing) what I thought became of the penny I gave her, then ſhe told, how her Mother eating no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing all the day before, took it from her, and bought therewith Sheeps Trotters for her dinner; I pittied her ſo much, that I borrowed a Groat of a Woman that cleans'd my Room, and ſent the Child immediately therewith to her Mother, without entring my Chamber all the while.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:132878:39"/> The <hi>Thurſday</hi> following, being the laſt day ſhe ever came to me, both ſhe and her Siſter came to Dine with me, alleading they had nothing to eat at home: After Dinner they were ſo unruly in the Priſon, that ſome won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred I would countenance ſuch Brats, but having relieved them ſo long, I would not deſiſt now I was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; but the wicked Mother inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſtop my deſign, for the <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following, ſhe came to my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, declaring I intended to Raviſh her Child, being not a little aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at her Impudence, and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling countenance, I wiſh'd her be gone like a wicked creature as ſhe was. I preſently concluded, that this Woman, having once ſaid ſuch a thing, might perhaps have the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to deſign the proof thereof, and might on purpoſe do her Child an Injury to put it on me. To prevent which, I entreated the Maſter of the Priſon to get a Juſtices Warrant for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:132878:39"/> the Mother and the Child, that the latter might be ſearch'd by a Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife; all which was perform'd in an hours time: The Midwife, after a full view of the Child, declared to the Juſtice, that there was nothing on her, but what was uſual to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, even from their Birth: That it was no more then any Child might have by running up a pair of Stairs, or at Play, of which the Juſtice made ſo little account, that he openly ſaid, it would come to nothing. To be ſure, I made preparations for the worſt, the which Mr. <hi>Church</hi> our Keeper underſtanding, often ſaid to me, that for a Groat he would ſtand Tryal for me, wiſhing me not to trouble my ſelf about any thoughts of that nature. Yet I imagin'd that in a matter of ſuch importance, I could not be too ſure, I therefore imploy'd one Mrs. <hi>Carpenter</hi> a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, (by chance then in Priſon) to procure another diſcreet Midwife, of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:132878:40"/> long Practiſe, and good knowledge, to view the Child for more Evidence, who inſtead thereof, got a Young Woman, called Mrs, <hi>Aſcu,</hi> and only a Deputy Midwife, to behold the Child, without letting me ſpeak to her before hand, contrary to my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections; both theſe began to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me to give my Adverſary a piece of Moneys to quiet her, in hopes to get a ſhare to themſelves, being both extream needy. I told them, it was not the opinion of ſuch a young Midwife I look'd for, and as for my Adverſary, I would expect ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction from her for the Injury ſhe had done, and knowing my ſelf Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, would rather Die than give her one penny to be Silent.</p>
               <p>I deſir'd alſo another Catholick Woman, by name Mrs. <hi>Tent,</hi> to find me out another experienced Midwife to inſpect the Child, and to witneſs what ſhe ayled; this told me ſhe knew one Mrs. <hi>James</hi> alſo a Catholick
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:132878:40"/> (a very ingenious Woman) who took the Oaths, only to diſſemble with the Times, and therefore might be very ſerviceable to me: My anſwer was, that if ever ſhe, or any belonging to her, expected any kindneſs from me, it would be on condition, that that cunning creature ſhould not have any thing to do in my affairs, which ſhe promiſed very often ſhe would not: yet as if Mrs. <hi>Carpenter</hi> and ſhe were agreed upon it to do me a prejudice, ſo that Mrs. <hi>Tent</hi> alſo, contrary to her promiſe and my will, brought the ſaid Mrs. <hi>James</hi> to my Adverſary, being alſo but a Deputy Midwife, and afterward had the confidence to bring her to my Chamber, and to wiſh me give her half a Crown for her pains, although ſhe was not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to behold the Child, I ask'd them by whoſe direction they were imploy'd, and ſo diſmiſs'd them.</p>
               <p>Now I began to believe for certain theſe Women were hired a purpoſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:132878:41"/> to ruin me; they intruded themſelves in my concerns what ever I did to hinder them: Yea; the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter,</hi> after all the warnings I gave her not to meddle any more in any thing belonging to me, brought me, notwithſtanding about the ſame time one Mrs. <hi>Ogle</hi> a Catholick, who by all means would have me compound with my Adverſary; I pray'd her to take no care thereof, for that I was advis'd to the contrary by an able Counſel; but ſeeing ſhe would not deſiſt encouraging my Adverſary with promiſes of procuring her a Reward to be ſilent, I writ to Mr. <hi>Aſton</hi> her Brother in Law, entreating him to pray her forbare medling in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, but all in vain; for ſome days after, this Mrs. <hi>Ogle,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter,</hi> came to my Chamber, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting me that they ſent the two forementioned Deputy Midwives, Mrs. <hi>James</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Aſcu</hi> to my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, to bring her to compoſition,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:132878:41"/> I much admired their confidence, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring by whoſe Authority they did incroach ſo much on me, letting them know, that what they did, was enough to find me Guilty, though the moſt Innocent in the World: whereupon I deſir'd a certain Woman I met in Priſon, to recall the ſaid Midwives, and to declare to my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, that I renounced any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition offer'd her in my Name; the two Deputy Midwives then came to my Chamber to meet the other two that imploy'd them, where I rayl'd at their impudence, in medling with my affairs without my own conſent; Mrs. <hi>Ogle</hi> (after all) wiſh'd them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back again, and compound the matter without me, ſince I was not to contribute a penny to what was to be given, adding beſides, I was fit for <hi>Bedlam</hi> for refuſing ſuch offers; little, as I ſuppoſe, immagining that my Adverſary was engag'd to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute me, and would have brought
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:132878:42"/> their moneys as a Teſtimony, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me, and thereby to have my Life.</p>
               <p>I thought it to no purpoſe to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any longer theſe obſtinate Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Reſolutions; I then began to reaſon the caſe with them, and how it behoved me rather to bring my Adverſary to juſt Puniſhment for ſcandalizing me, ſince God, my own Conſcience, and many Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were Witneſſes of my Innocency. And for their further ſatisfaction, I deſired God to ſhew no Mercy to my Soul, if ever I enter'd that Childs Body a hairs breadth, as was reported, or ever intended any ſuch thing. The two Midwives being pitiful poor, as alſo Mrs. <hi>Carpenter,</hi> who liveth on Charity, knowing, that if they came to compoſition, themſelves would go ſnacks with my Adverſary. They were going by Mrs. <hi>Ogles</hi> directions to know the leaſt ſhe would accept of: I followed them untiI they came
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:132878:42"/> to the Common ſide, where I deſired all the Priſoners to take notice, that thoſe two Women were going to compound with my Adverſary with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my conſent; upon this they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in a fury to my Chamber among the reſt, where I did not go until they departed.</p>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Ogle</hi> after all, being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with theſe three Indigents, loſt no time to encourage my Adverſary with hopes of ſome moneys, the only thing ſhe aimed at; who thereupon made it her buſineſs daily to get part thereof in hand. How they agreed I do not know, only I was told, that my Adverſary in preſence of Mrs. <hi>Ogle</hi> deſired the Juſtice that iſſued out his Warrant againſt me, to withdraw her Action, and that ſome body in Malice perſwaded the Child to accuſe me, but it ſeems the Juſtice engag'd her to a Tryal.</p>
               <p>Now, the two Midwives, mad I did not yield to a Compoſition, aſſur'd
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:132878:43"/> my Adverſary, if ſhe Proſecuted me, they would be both Witneſſes for her at my Tryal, where none beſides them two and the Child, with her Mother, appeared againſt me, that ever ſaw my face before; yet I was caſt upon the ſole Oath of the ſaid Mrs. <hi>James,</hi> a Catholick Deputy Midwife, brought to be my Witneſs by ſome pretended friends of my own Religion; all the reſt onely ſaid, <hi>They ſaw the Child in ſuch a manner;</hi> which leſs reflected on me, then on any elſe, ſhe being abroad among all ſorts of people. Mrs. <hi>James</hi> took her Oath, I own'd the Fact to her, in preſence of four more, and that I offer'd Ten pounds to ſmother it, although the ſaid four, to wit, Mrs. <hi>Pennay,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Ogle,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Carpenter,</hi> three Catholicks, and Mrs. <hi>Aſcu</hi> a Proteſtant, could witneſs her to be Perjur'd; as alſo five or ſix Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, having never ſpoken to her but twice, once when Mrs. <hi>Tent</hi> brought her to my Chamber, wiſhing
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:132878:43"/> me to give her half a Crown, and the ſecond time in the preſence of the ſaid Gentlewomen and Priſoners, yet none appear'd at Court to juſtifie the Truth. The Priſoners could not, without ſo many <hi>Habeas Corpus's,</hi> which the Juſtices of the Peace had no Authority to grant, nor was it in my power to be at the expences thereof: The Gentlewomen preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they durſt not be ſeen, leaſt they ſhould be put to trouble for their Religion, although I took my Oath I would not call for their Names be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had obtain'd a Promiſe from the Court not to moleſt them, ſo that I was brought in guilty of a Treſpaſs.</p>
               <p>And thus I had loſt my life by mrs. <hi>James,</hi> if the Grand Jury had found the Bill to be Fellony, of all which, I conceive the ſaid Catholick Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women to be as guilty as the ſaid Mrs. <hi>James,</hi> ſince they engaged her in my concerns againſt my will, and that they refuſed to juſtifie the truth of what I ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:132878:44"/>
               <p>On my ſide there were above twenty Proteſtant Witneſſes beſides Catholicks. One Miſtris <hi>Watſon</hi> the moſt reputed Midwife in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and who viewed the Child, the very firſt day by order of a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of Peace, with two Women more of very good credit and repute, and very Skilful in Midwifry, took their Oaths before the Bench, that the Child as far as could appear to the beſt experienced Midwives was never touch'd by man, that what was ſeen on her was incident to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Children by Playing or running up ſtairs.</p>
               <p>I had in Court four Certificates under the hands of four different Parties, who examined the Child in the beginning a part, quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent one from the other: At my Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſhe learn'd another Leſſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all the reſt; She added, that Striving with me, ſhe tor'd my Ruffles, altho' there was in Court
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:132878:44"/> the Seamſter from whom I bought them, and my Waſh-woman; the one was ready to Sware that ſhe made me but the Ten payers then produc'd in Court; and the other, that the ſaid Ten payers, which ſhe waſhed often, were all the Ruffles I had, which never wanted the mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one ſtitch with a Needle.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Child was taught to ſay, that a certain Woman heard her cry, when I offer'd violence to her, which the ſame Woman not onely deny'd, being not in my Chamber in ſix or ſeven months before this Report, but alſo told in Court, that my Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, with her Husband, offer'd her moneys to ſay ſo.</p>
               <p>The Child being demanded by the Court, how often did I attempt to abuſe her, ſhe ſaid only twice, to wit, the <hi>Munday</hi> before her Mother accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me, and about three weeks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that. Now every one may ſee the wickedneſs of this Childs Mother,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:132878:45"/> who, contrary to my orders, ſent her Daughter to me, as I have reaſon to believe, purpoſely to Trapan me: 'Tis true, the Child came twice to my Chamber alone in Eleven weeks time, that is ſince I warn'd the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to keep her at home. The firſt time was the day I went to give Bayle before a Judge, but then ſhe did not enter my Room, as ſeven Men and Women were ready to Witneſs, whom I left in my Chamber going out when I met the Child by the way, but had not leiſure to ask what ſhe came for.</p>
               <p>The ſecond time was the <hi>Munday</hi> before mentioned, when I gave her the penny, for which her Mother bought Sheeps Trotters, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Goat, as I ſaid before, out of pitty, and this in another Room, in preſence of a Priſoner, at which time this Child went away as waggiſh as ever. Her coming with her Siſter the <hi>Thurſday</hi> following to Dine with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:132878:45"/> me, being the laſt time I ſpoke to her, and their unrulineſs before many Priſoners, juſtifieth ſhe was not offer'd any violence the <hi>Munday</hi> before, yet the <hi>Saturday</hi> following her Mother vented her malicious deſigns of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicing me, unleſs ſhe got the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys demanded.</p>
               <p>Behold the ungratefulneſs of this generation of Vipers: I relieved with part of my Dinner about ten weeks this Childs Mother, whom I ſaw was ſtarving in Priſon, and ſucking of Bones I ſet aſide for a Dog, during which time, I allowed to buy food for her Sucking Child, a penny, two pence, or three pence dayly; after her being at Liberty, I aſſiſted her whole Family, every other day, for near a years time; I beſtowed on her Husband an old Suit of Cloaths, Hat, Shoes, Stockings, and Gloves; and on both her Daughters, moneys for the Cloaths they wore; and for their Schooling half a year; they having
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:132878:46"/> not a Shift to their backs, nor Shoes to their feet, but what I bought for them. And becauſe moneys grew ſcarce with me, that I could not continue my Charity, I muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with Iniquity; I muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed to offer violence to her Child the only two times ſhe came alone to me, and againſt my will in eleven weeks ſpace, having never offer'd any ſuch the whole year before, as the Child own'd it in open Court, altho ſhe came to me every other day. Beſides, what likelihood there is, that I had the leaſt thought thereof, when I could have had her every day in my Chamber at a words ſpeaking, and that on the contrary, I forbid her coming at all; but the matter was, the Mother was ſet on by my compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions friends, and was promiſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, which ſhe was willing to accept at any ſcore; believing, if I were once at liberty, ſhe ſhould never ſee me any more, as ſhe often ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:132878:46"/>
               <p>This wicked Woman being ask'd by ſeveral, why ſhe pretended her Child was abus'd, when ſhe ran and play'd all day long, and look'd as well as ever ſhe did; to which ſhe anſwered divers times, as was juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in Court by her neareſt Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that her Child ayl'd nothing, but that ſhe would have moneys from the Papiſt Rogue. Yet although ſhe had ſcarce one witneſs for her, but was known in the Pariſh, to be either a Whore, a Thief, or Perjur'd Creature; as I was creedibly inform'd; and that none of them ever ſaw my face but in Court, excepting the two Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives, that were brought by Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks to be for me, notwithſtanding upon the falſe Oath of one of them, a Woman of a very bad Repute, I was caſt, as I ſaid before.</p>
               <p>All being conſidered, 'tis not to be doubted, but this evil befel me by the inſtigation and malice of the five Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Prieſts and Jeſuits, my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:132878:47"/> companions; for firſt, my Adverſary being pitiful poor, and wanting Bread, could not Fee a Counſel, and Proſecute me without having aſſiſtance from others: Who then would encourage her, but thoſe who ſaught all occaſions to prejudice me, whoſe Pentioners in Priſon, gave my <hi>Adverſary</hi> every day a full account of what preparations I made for my own defence.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Mr. <hi>O BRYAN.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>They imploy'd one Mr. <hi>O Bryan,</hi> a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, whilſt I relieved him with Mony and half my Dinner, as often as he told me he wanted Bread, to corrupt my Witneſſes, and keep correſpondence with my Adverſary, who thereupon got into favour among Catholicks, being before in bad repute with them; this man being well vers'd in ſuch Subtilties, as appeared in his conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy againſt the Duke of <hi>B.</hi> for which he ſtands charg'd in ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds dammage, and to ſtand
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:132878:47"/> in the Pillory, as alſo while he wrote under Doctor <hi>Tongue</hi> as a pretended Proteſtant, making now profeſſion to be a Roman Catholick, getting the opportunity in my Chamber to Steal from me ſome old Letters, by which he Learn'd ſo well to counterfeit my hand, that he writ a Letter in my Name to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> rayling at the Catholick Religion, by ſhewing which to Catholicks, he got to himſelf great eſteem for diſcovering a thing I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, either by Letter or Petition, or any other means: Afterwards underſtanding I confirm'd the ſame by a Solemne Oath to Friends, then he adds, I writ for certain ſuch a Letter, but I did not ſend it. To which I anſwer, that I take God to Witneſs, I never writ any ſuch Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the ſaid Arch Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> nor ever intended as yet to write. But this is but part of his Mallice and Subtilties. Now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:132878:48"/> I am Writing a Book in my own Vindication which reflects on him, and on the reſt of my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, he is taken up in new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions againſt me, for which he is rewarded by my Adverſaries, and the upholders of their Calumny; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially by Mrs. <hi>Catharine Sheldon</hi> and other mannagers of the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: among other Lies, he Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes that there are ſeveral Points in this Book (which he never ſaw as yet) againſt the Catholick Religion. That I loſt my Imployment with an Ambaſſador, for being found by him and his men, making uſe of a Woman at Night in the open Streets. I leave the examination of the Truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Earl of <hi>Fingale,</hi> and an hundred others that can teſtifie the contrary, as alſo the unprobability of the thing.</p>
                  <p>'Tis not to be queſtioned, but that this man was the firſt Inventer of the Childs Mother Stratagem, thereby
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:132878:48"/> to ingratiate himſelf with my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and conſequently with other Catholicks, otherwiſe, who can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that one I never once offended in the leaſt, and whom I endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to oblige to the utmoſt of my power, by offering him half my Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner while we continued Priſoners; by recommending him to every one I knew, having procur'd him above Twenty ſhillings at once, beſides what moneys I beſtowed on him of my own, ſhould take an opportunity, while I ſent for ſome things for his Eating, to Steal old papers from me to learn to counterfeit my hand; and this before the Childs Mother accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me, unleſs he deſigned this evil to me. This appears clearly by the following circumſtances; for the third day after this Stratagem was divulg'd, a certain Catholick Woman being ſome days before Releaſed out of Priſon, knowing every thing that paſs'd in my Room, which ſhe kept
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:132878:49"/> clean daily, offer'd of her own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, to juſtifie ſeveral things about the Child to my advantage, which the foreſaid Mr. <hi>Bryan</hi> underſtanding, got the opportunity to call her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately to another Room, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her from being my Witneſs, as ſhe ſelf told me afterwards, declaring to her, I was to forſake my Religion, and that ſhe would incur the Catholicks diſpleaſure; ſo that when I deſir'd her to give me in writing, before Witneſſes, what ſhe could ſay; I could not get a word out of her mouth; at laſt, ſhe ſaid, I know what you write down is true, yet I do not deſire to be concern'd. All this while I thought this Mr. <hi>Bryan</hi> to be my ſpecial friend, therefore I had choſen him for one of my Witneſſes of what ſhe could ſay; but whilſt twelve lines were a reading, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted me five times, alleadging he was then buſie, he could not ſtay, he muſt go to Dinner, and ſo depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:132878:49"/> altho I invited him to Dine with me, and that I told him that what I was about concern'd my Life. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afterwards told by the Priſoners (to my great amazement) how I was betray'd by him, and how he diſwaded the Woman from being my Witneſs, as ſhe her ſelf told me afterwards, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving no Gentleman would do as he did, or betray his Friends with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any occaſion of diſpleaſure, I enquir'd of his old acquaintance what he was.</p>
                  <p>One Mrs. <hi>Tent</hi> a Taylors Wife did truly aſſure me, ſhe knew him four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or fifteen years ago in <hi>Dublin,</hi> where ſhe kept an houſe of entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and when he us'd frequently thither playing at Cards, and getting his livelyhood by falſe Dice, his name then being not <hi>O Bryan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item</hi> one <hi>Turner</hi> from the County of <hi>Wexford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein he had Thirty Pounds a year of his own inheritance formerly, being known in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:132878:50"/> 
                     <hi>London</hi> to all thoſe that knew him about St. <hi>James</hi> in the quality of a Porter, to be a moſt honeſt and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs man, did declare unto me, that the ſaid <hi>O Bryan</hi> was Born in the ſame County of <hi>Wexford</hi> with him: That he knew his Father and his Mother, but of another Name, and a Farmer. That their Sons Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Name is indeed <hi>Bryan:</hi> That all the conſiderable Towns and Villages, this <hi>Bryan</hi> divulg'd, did belong here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore to his Predeceſſors, were to his knowledg the Lands of other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who had the Inheritance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of from their Fore-Fathers. Others that knew his Siſter in Town here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ten years, can Witneſs ſhe never went by the Name of <hi>O Bryan.</hi> 'Tis certain himſelf told me, how my Lord <hi>O Bryan,</hi> who countenanc'd him in <hi>Holland</hi> as his name ſake, being there inform'd he was not the man he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended himſelf to be, gave orders to forbid him his houſe, yet he ſaid he
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:132878:50"/> juſtified himſelf afterwards in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſaid <hi>Bryan</hi> being ask'd by me, before we fell out, what he did up ſo exceſſive late every night, his anſwer was, he Studied deſigns. Well may I now be diſcredited, ſince all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions againſt me are rewarded with Moneys, and aſſerted for reall truth to every one by Mrs. <hi>Catharine Sheldon,</hi> and the reſt of the Upholders of my Adverſaries Calumnies. My comfort is, that he is only countenac'd by thoſe who regard his Perſon more then his Honeſty, he being a proper well Lim'd man. Others, as he on the like account, having occaſioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reſt of my Troubles.</p>
                  <p>All being conſidered, I was not only deceived in him, but alſo the Duke of <hi>B.</hi> and ſeveral others: Having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me that he was Heir to 4000 Acres of Land, I reliev'd him as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: he aſſur'd me, that his Grand-father and Uncle were both Knighted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:132878:51"/> by the particular favours of this Duke of <hi>B.</hi> father; a cunning device to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade this Noble Duke not to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute him for his foreſaid late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt his Grace. <hi>Item,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding from me the name of the Lady that ſent him the Guinney on my requeſt, he preſently told me, he was near related to her Husband, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> and doubtleſs he had ſince conſiderable Relief on that account, the Gentleman himſelf being not in the Kingdome to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict him. A brave man to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to perſecute honeſt men!</p>
                  <p>'Tis no wonder he was ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary skilful in his own Petegree, ſince he made it his Trade to juſtifie (by his ingenuity) thoſe he never knew but by chance. One Mr. <hi>King</hi> heretofore Servant to the Duke of <hi>Gl.</hi> and very well known to all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> did aſſure me in this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the forenamed <hi>O Bryan,</hi> made it his Practiſe, being at Liberty
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:132878:51"/> to counterfeit Atteſtations for ſeveral Women, who make it their buſineſs to go a Begging all <hi>England</hi> over, ſome as pretended Miniſters Wives, and others of other concerns, whoſe houſes were deſtroy'd and burnt by Tories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I know by experience in my Travels abroad, that the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> has ſufficient occaſion to bemoan the Injuſtice done to it, by the Practitioners of ſuch falſe Atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations and Commendations. I know that pitiful mechanick people, whoſe Predeceſſors never had one ſix pence Revenue, betook the names of the greateſt Noblemen in that Kingdom in their Letters of Recommendations, gathering under that Notion, great ſums of Moneys in <hi>France, Spain, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> having their own Commorades, their Pages, Footmen, and <hi>Vale du Chambers.</hi> I know they us'd that Trade ſo often in them parts, that the name of an <hi>Iriſhman</hi> among them is moſt odious; admiring that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:132878:52"/> pretended Gentlemen, and perſons of Quality, did not know common Breeding, and were all Beggars. <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> men can teſtifie part of theſe Cheats, if they will but call to mind their old acquaintance <hi>Claucy,</hi> moſt notorious in ſuch ſubtilties: If Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks did but conſider any of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, they would not ſo fluently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the foreſaid <hi>O Bryan</hi> for every lying Letter ſent to ſome of them againſt me, unleſs they deſignedly countenance him in what he doth, as certainly the upholders of my Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries Calumny have often done, who underſtanding I intended to bring ſome of their Friends to queſtion for what they machinated againſt me; nothing then muſt ſatisfie them but my Life, of which they might have eaſily deprived me, by the aſſiſtance of certain Women they made uſe of to that purpoſe, had the Grand Jury no more Conſcience than they; for the ſaid Women forc'd on me two
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:132878:52"/> Midwives, with deſign to take away my Life, for otherwiſe, would any ordinary creatures, as they were, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to juſtifie the Truth to ſave ones life, and eſpecially of a Catholick as they were, if they did not purpoſely deſign my Death: Alſo, can any one believe, if they did not reſolve to have my Life, but they had ſo much command on theſe two Midwives they chooſe to be my Witneſſes, as to diſſwade them at leaſt from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting me, which they might have done by once ſpeaking to them. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, can any believe that the ſaid Mrs. <hi>James</hi> would dare juſtifie by a falſe Oath in open Court, what the ſaid four Gentlewomen beſides ſeven or eight Priſoners, could witneſs to be a Lie, unleſs it was concluded upon before hand, that none of them would appear againſt her, and that the Priſoners could not.</p>
                  <p>One Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> a Catholick, being familiarly acquainted with my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:132878:53"/> and one of thoſe that firſt took the Childs Examination, would not juſtifie the ſame at Court, becauſe I told, it contradicted what the ſaid Child ſaid to others, leaſt ſhe ſhould do me any ſervice therein; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, both ſhe and her Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Mrs. <hi>Cottee</hi> a Catholick, did ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate the matter to exceſs in all Companies, and this only out of mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, becauſe this <hi>Greys</hi> Brother was Married to one of my Adverſaries Siſters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> one Mrs. <hi>Martha</hi> a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and an old Servant to the Lady <hi>St.</hi> underſtanding from one of my Proteſtant Witneſſes, what ſhe could juſtifie in my behalf, ſaid, without conſidering what I had to ſay for my ſelf, I deſerv'd to be Puniſh'd, which diſcourag'd ſo this Witneſs, that ſhe did not declare a word of what ſhe promiſs'd, and this only becauſe one of my Adverſaries Father was her fellow Servant.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:132878:53"/>
                  <p>You may ſee what Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks we have in theſe days; and how can we expect them to be otherwiſe, when thoſe who ought by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to inſtruct them in Virtue and Truth, are themſelves the chief In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Evil, and the promoters of Calumny and Lies, as I have juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the above five reputed prieſts and Jeſuits, beſides others already mentioned.</p>
                  <p>It pleaſed God, after all their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that the Court onely Fin'd me to the Head Bayliff of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who underſtanding my Poverty, was willing to forgive me his Fine, but my Adverſaries to detain me a Priſoner, leaſt I brought them to an account (as was Reported) of their miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours, imploy'd one <hi>Nicholas Crouch</hi> a Catholick to divulge of me that I was a Wealthy man, although they knew in their Conſcience (if they had any) that I could not pay one penny in an hundred of the ſum ſet
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:132878:54"/> on me. This Schollar of theirs a Solliciter by calling, writ me a dozen Letters that he would do me a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, unleſs I ſatisfied him in a moſt unjuſt demand, although he borrow'd of me about three pounds, and never paid me as yet: ſuch are the griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances Priſoners are lyable to.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The true deſcription of Wicked Women.</head>
                  <p>Two againſt one is hard meaſure, but half a dozen to one is inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; yet I believe it is eaſier to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the fury of twenty Rational men, then of one Incens'd woman. Mallice and Envy is the laſt gaſp of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting Life, and if ſhe Sounds or falls into a trance, her firſt thoughts are after her recovery. Obſtinacy is the ground of her Fury, and Reaſon the leaſt of her thoughts. Self will is the beſt of her underſtanding, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:132878:54"/> Juſtice is an horrour to her Intereſt. The deſire of her friend is her Law, and whom he hates is her mortal Enemy, although her conſtancy is guided by the Weather-cock. Vanity is the fruits of her labours, and to be flatter'd is her great delight. Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation is ſo beneath her, that the very motion thereof incenſes her the more; ſo that woe to him that is entangled in her Hooks. 'Tis certain all the Devils in Hell can never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice man more than a wicked Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> after denying Chriſt, by the mallice of ſuch a Creature, is ſaid to have given this deſcription of her: A Woman is more Pitiful than Man, more Envious than a Tyrant, more Malicious than a Serpent, and more deceitful than the Devil. But this doth not in the leaſt reflect on Virtuous and good Women.</p>
                  <p>It was my misfortune to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnar'd by one I never offended in the leaſt, and yet to comply with her
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:132878:55"/> Friend, ſhe has done me all the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice imaginable: I muſt confeſs Mrs: <hi>Catharine Sheldon</hi> in the begining of her rage againſt me has compel'd certain thoughts in my Head, the like I never harbour'd before, nor ſince; for all my Adverſaries together could never do me the hundreth part of the prejudice I received, had ſhe not back'd them She never ſaw but in Priſon, which cannot but reflect much on her reputation, in forſaking one ſhe knew for twelve years before, and in countenancing the greateſt Injuſtice that can be for ſtrangers ſakes, altho ſhe was not concern'd therein in the leaſt; and that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave her, or any belonging to her, except theſe my juſt complaints, as yet any occaſion of diſpleaſure: She can only ſay I would not yield to ſome extravagant propoſitions of my Adverſaries, her Friends; and that I ſaid I would bring ſome of them to account for their Injuſtice to me, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:132878:55"/> yet there is no evil but She has pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd againſt my Reputation, my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and my Livelyhood.</p>
                  <p>'Tis evident there is nothing She wiſh'd more then my Death, and ſince God I hope has given her no power thereon, ſhe is reſolv'd to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Liberty by diſwading Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks from beſtowing me any Relief towards my Releaſe out of Priſon; aſſuring them, I intend as ſoon as I am at Liberty, to impeach as well other Catholicks, as my Adverſaries, ſo that ſhe has done what lay in her Power to detain me always in Priſon, or to Starve me therein.</p>
                  <p>My only requeſt to the managers of the Charities given weekly for the maintenance of Catholick Priſoners was, that ſince I could be at Liberty any time this half year by paying an inconſiderable Sum of Moneys I owe, They would be pleaſed to allow my ſhare of the ſaid Charities to my Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors in the ſame manner it is paid
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:132878:56"/> me, until my Debts was ſatisfied. Who doubts but the Doners or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowers of ſuch Charities would rather Grant their Moneys to releaſe Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, then to maintain them in Goal, as one of our beſt Benefactors has intimated to me already? yet Mrs. <hi>Catharine Sheldons</hi> bad Character of me has ſent ſuch a terror in the Harts of the Diſtributors of the ſaid Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that they have rejected all ſuch Overtures.</p>
                  <p>After this, a certain Lady of Quality was pleaſed to Collect among her acquaintance near the Sum deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for my Releaſe, the which <hi>Mrs. Catharine Sheldon</hi> alſo hindred to be given me, by Publickly divulging that this Book is full of Invectives againſt the Catholick Religion, and that I am a deſerter thereof: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Peruſeth the ſame, will find no ſuch thing, and therefore may juſtly conclude how falſe the reſt of her Accuſations be. Behold what a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:132878:56"/> Scourge She is to me among my other afflictions! If ſhe was ask'd from whence ſhe had this Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhe cannot deny but ſhe got it from the foreſaid <hi>Bryan,</hi> a moſt Treacherous Man; or from Mr. <hi>Power</hi> a moſt notorious Hipocrite, or from ſome others of my Adverſaries; which ſhews a great deal of Mallice in her to me, and very little Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Wiſdome, for giving credit to the Calumnies of my Adverſaries, ſince the World knows there is no belief in the words of an Enemy.</p>
                  <p>I wonder ſhe is ſo Subject to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Flying reports, unleſs She knows her own Reverend Brother to be guilty of what was ſaid of him, to which I never gave as yet any Faith. It would be expedient for her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to be able to juſtifie one truth among hundred of Lyes She divulg'd of me theſe thirteen months paſt, I being now a Priſoner two years and a half, all which time I
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:132878:57"/> never ſaw her face. I am confident ſhe will never find out one Lawfull and juſt Proof in confirmation of any one of her Scandalous reports of me; altho' I can find five hundred to confute her and her conſorts, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I ſuffer as if what ſhe Publiſh'd of me was as true as the Goſpell. I do not know to whom better to compare this Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans cruelty to me (that never gave her any juſt diſtaſte in my Life) then to thoſe Women who Munder their own Fleſh and Blood, the Fruits of their Womb, their dear and harmleſs Children, whom neither the fear of God, nor of the Laws of the Land could diſſwade from ſo inhuman an Act, no more then my moſt civil Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, my preſent condition and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, could prevail with the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Catharine Sheldon</hi> not to proſecute me, one of her beſt Wiſhers in the Land.</p>
                  <p>Hence is clearly to be underſtood,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:132878:57"/> that the Mrs. <hi>Catharine Sheldon</hi> was the Principal Inſtrument for procuring thoſe Catholick Women that brought the two Midwives to be my Witneſſes, and afterwards perſwaded them to Swear againſt me at my Tryal.</p>
                  <p>But ſince God and my own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience are Witneſs of the wrongs done me, I thought it moſt neceſſary for the ſatisfaction of the World, to commit the whole Circumſtance of every particular to the Preſs; not doubting but the Impartial Reader will comprehend as well the Injuſtice done me, as if he had been an Eye Witneſs to all my Actions, nothing being contain'd in this Book, but what I might leave on my Death to be true.</p>
                  <p>I was forc'd, for want of Moneys to beſtow the whole ſale of the Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies to the Printer; And whoſoever blames me for Printing the ſame, would undoubtedly do worſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:132878:58"/> in the like occaſion. If any one of them was Robb'd of his whole Store or Patrimony, or was falſly accuſed of any Fellonious Action, by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Prieſt or Jeſuit, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied Reſtitution of Goods and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, would he not Proſecute him, without any regard to the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of his Religion? I have been Robb'd of my Reputation, of my Livelyhood, and of all future expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of conſiderable Imployments by the Calumny of my Adverſaries, and their ſupporters; and who can juſtly find fault with me for putting the Saddle on the right Horſe?</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Fiat Juſtitia, vel ruat Caelum</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>W. Downing</hi> in <hi>Bartholomew-Cloſe</hi> Printer, 1681</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
